Guide to the Arthur H. and Mary Marden Dean Lafayette Collection, 1520-1973
Lafayette Collection (Arthur H. and Mary Marden Dean Lafayette Collection), 1520-1973
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Arthur H. and Mary Marden Dean Lafayette Collection, 1520-1973
4611
Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de Lafayette, 1757-1834.
49.6 linear ft.
Manuscripts, correspondence, documents, broadsides, microfilms, graphics, books, memorabilia.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
The Lafayette Collection contains materials by, to or about Lafayette and his family, with family documents extending back to 1245 and through the death of Georges Washington Lafayette in 1849. The series "Medals and Coins" covers a century and a half, up to 1931. The collection includes the oldest existing letter from Lafayette (1772), long missives he sent to his wife from America during the Revolution, other letters he wrote while imprisoned in Austria (1792-1797) and during his 1824-5 trip to the USA; texts of Lafayette's speeches, his commentary on public events, material compiled for inclusion in his memoirs, financial statements; many letters from foreign correspondents on the progress of liberal causes in their countries, including letters from leaders of the Italian revolutionary movement; notes concerning the Belgian revolution, letters and documents on his involvement in the Italian and Polish revolutions, and documents concerning the management of family business affairs, including the management of the family estates. Some of the more remarkable documents were put on display for the exhibition "Lafayette, Citizen of Two Worlds" (October 2007-May 2008), whose electronic version is accessible online at http://rmc.library.cornell.edu/lafayette/.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert du Motier, marquis de Lafayette was born at Chavaniac, Auvergne, in 1757, to an old, illustrious family of the provincial and military nobility. He lost both his parents early: his father was killed by the British at the Battle of Minden when Lafayette was two years old (1759), and when he was thirteen and attending the prestigious Collège de Plessis in Paris both his mother and grandfather died (1770). The latter's death left Lafayette with a sizable inheritance: he was actually the richest bachelor in France. In 1771 Lafayette became one of the King's Musketeers, beginning the military career he had always envisioned for himself. In February of 1773 he moved to Versailles as a protégé of Jean de Noailles, the Duc d'Ayen, becoming a lieutenant in the Noailles Dragoons in April and promoted to captain one year later, shortly after his arranged marriage to the Duc d'Ayen's daughter, Adrienne de Noailles on April 11, 1774. And yet, Lafayette's chances at obtaining a position matching his wealth and status were curtailed by the prevailing reformist mood and when the Ministry of War cut costs and suppressed his regiment, he was relegated to reserve status (June1776.)
Lafayette first heard of the American revolt in 1775, at a dinner given by his commander the comte de Broglie in Metz. Inspired to serve the American cause though he knew very little about America beyond what he had read in Raynal and what he heard from Franklin, Lafayette managed to sign on as a future major-general in the American army in December 1776. But although by this time the French government was sending covert aid to the Americans in the hope of securing French trade interests (the "arms-for-tobacco deal"), Lafayette had to buy his own ship,La Victoire. It sailed from Spain on April 20, 1777 and arrived at North Island, South Carolina on June 13, 1777. Initially disappointed to find himself a general without a command, Lafayette was to return to France in 1782 having earned gloire for himself as well as liberty for the American colonies.
When Lafayette met George Washington on July 31, 1777, it was the start of a famous and long-lasting friendship, often described as a "father-son relationship." Lafayette first saw combat at Brandywine (September 11, 1777). The leg wound that he got there lent him military credibility, and he received command of the Virginia division of the Continental Army, with which he spent the winter at Valley Forge under nearly unlivable conditions. In 1778 Lafayette took part in battles at Barren Hill and Monmouth Court House and served with the Continental detachment in Rhode Island in conjunction with d'Estaing's expeditionary force. Earlier that year, Congress had chosen Lafayette to lead a campaign into Canada, but the campaign was ultimately abandoned as unfeasible.
Lafayette returned to a France that was now officially an ally of the United States at the beginning of 1779. He was thus in France for the birth of his son George Washington Lafayette, as he had not been when Adrienne de Lafayette gave birth to their second daughter, Anastasie (1777), and buried Henriette, their first (1778). During this year at home, in addition to pleading the American cause to his compatriots, Lafayette was appointed to the French army as it prepared to invade England. The invasion never came about, and Lafayette was in America again by April 1780. In February 1781, Lafayette led a detachment against troops led by the traitor Benedict Arnold. Later that year he commanded forces against Cornwallis in the decisive campaign of the American war.
Lafayette returned to France in 1782 a popular hero and lobbyist for American economic interests. He accepted the position of quartermaster general of a Franco-Spanish expeditionary force that was headed for British Canada, and then the position of maréchal de camp in 1783, the year peace was officially declared in the United States. His second daughter Virginie was born in September. In these inter-revolutionary years, Lafayette energetically involved himself in the liberal causes of his day. He had been a member of the Freemasons since 1775 but in 1782 publicly identified himself with this network of secret societies that, with the literary salons of the day, formed pockets of free thought within the ancient regime and eventually espoused liberal politics. Lafayette devoted himself especially to the causes of toleration for French Protestants, whom he visited in Cévennes in 1785. In one of his most original enterprises, he also purchased a plantation in the French colony of Guiana which was to be the site of an experiment in gradually emancipating black slaves so as to maximize both their chances at integration into free society, and their productivity and birth rate. Madame Lafayette oversaw the management of the plantation after the death of its appointed manager, Richeprey, in 1786. During the 1780s, Lafayette's international popularity was evidenced by his first "American Tour" in 1784 and an "European Tour" in 1785, the highlight of which was a personal meeting with the "enlightened despot" Frederick II of Prussia.
Lafayette's role in the French Revolution was conditioned by the several aspects of his public identity, as paternalistic aristocrat, enthusiastic defender of freedoms, self-serving hero, and soldier. In 1787 and 1788, Lafayette attended sessions of the Assembly of Notables, called at this time to resolve pressing taxation issues. To the Assembly Lafayette brought his call for the civil rights of Protestants (an Edict of Toleration was in fact enacted in November of 1787). In 1789 Lafayette represented the nobility when he was elected deputy to the Estates General, a long inactive governing institution which now joined with the Third Estate to become the National Assembly. Lafayette presented the "Déclaration de droits de l'homme et du citoyen" to the Assembly on July 11, 1789, and was chosen vice-president of the National Assembly on the eve of the Fall of the Bastille. In the turbulence that followed, Lafayette was proclaimed commandant of the Garde Nationale, with the charge of keeping order in the streets of Paris, a task in which his popular sway among the moderate bourgeoisie aided him. The Guard escorted the King and Queen to Paris in October of 1789. On July 14, 1790, he presided at the Fête de la Federation.
Criticism of Lafayette intensified when he ordered his men to fire on the unruly crowd at the Champs de Mars in 1791. In October of that year Lafayette resigned as commandant of the Garde Nationale of Paris. In 1792 he became a commander in the war with Austria, which began in April. Lafayette's censure of the increasing influence of Jacobinism, and his basic inability to understand political trends, placed him at odds with both the government and the opposition. He was publicly accused of plotting to march on Paris with his troops. On August 19, 1792, the National Convention, formed after the arrest of Louis XVI on August 10, replaced Lafayette with Dumouriez, who dumbed him "a traitor" after he emigrated. Lafayette was in fact intercepted by the Austrians and imprisoned for five years -- first at Wesel, then at Magdebourg, Neisse and Olmütz. Adrienne Lafayette and the children, who had been experiencing the revolution from the provinces, joined him in prison in 1795. Adrienne herself had been in jail in France, and had survived the guillotining of her mother, grandmother and elder sister. The Lafayette family was more fortunate; save George who was staying in America, they together bore two more years of imprisonment. Freed in 1797, Lafayette remained on the list of proscribed émigrés, living in exile in Holstein and Holland until 1799. Adrienne, meanwhile, was in France (1797-1799) trying to get permission for her husband's return and to recover part of her inheritance: the Directory had confiscated and sold all of Lafayette's properties in Bretagne and Auvergne except for the house at Chavaniac.
With the establishment of the Consulate in November 1799 (the "18th Brumaire") the political climate in France changed enough that Lafayette was able to repatriate. He retired to La Grange (part of Adrienne's inheritance), where, during the years of the Consulate and Empire (1800-1815), he led a relatively private life, pursuing the interest in modern agriculture that he had developed in prison, and absorbed in the day to day management of his estate and of his financial crises: Lafayette's extremely generous financing of two revolutions, in combination with the loss of his properties, left him deep in debt. In 1804 the American government expressed their gratitude for Lafayette's contribution to the Revolutionary War by granting him a tract of land in Louisiana, but this gift, like the Florida Lands granted him later, in 1824, turned out to be something of a liability, in that his attempts to sell portions of it to his creditors embroiled him in lawsuits and the lands themselves were, in some cases, already occupied by settlers. Adrienne, in ill health since her imprisonment, died in 1807.
With the Restoration (1815-1830) Lafayette was once more drawn into political life, in the liberal opposition. In 1815 he served several terms in the Chamber of Deputies, and insisted on Napoleon Bonaparte's abdication. Lafayette played a leading role in the "Glorious Revolution" of July 1830 and found himself again commandant of the Garde Nationale. He was now in his seventies. His decision to support the duc d'Orléans' accession to the throne seemed to some a betrayal of his role as defender of the republican ideals.
During the Restoration years La Grange became a mecca for Lafayette's many admirers. His popularity grew even more with his American Tour of 1824-1825 as city after city hailed Lafayette as almost another "Father of Our Country."
Finally, in the last years of his life, Lafayette, still true to his motto, "Cur non?" supported national insurrections in Belgium (1830) and Poland (1831). He had followed Belgian politics since 1789 when the Brabant revolted against Austrian domination, and the chief of the Flemish Catholic party, Van der Noot, was in contact with the French government through the mediation of Lafayette. As the President of the Comité Central en Faveur des Polonais (1830-1832), Lafayette was active in fundraising and in publicizing the plight of Poland and its refugees. He also during this time corresponded with many members of the Carbonari, revolutionary Italians involved in the 1831 uprising. Lafayette died in Paris on May 20, 1834.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
The Lafayette Collection contains more than 11,000 items documenting all aspects of the public and private life of Gilbert du Motier, marquis de Lafayette (1757-1834).
The guide to the Lafayette collection was produced with funding provided by the United States Department of Education grant Title II-C, "Strengthening Research Library Resources": The French Revolution Collections at Cornell University: a Retrospective Conversion and Preservation Project.
Project staff included Jean V. Callahan, Peggy John, and Isabel Rivera. The initial Lafayette website (guide and exhibit) was conceived by Jean V. Callahan and implemented by Noni Korf Vidal. In 2007, major improvements were made by Laurent Ferri, curator of the exhibition "Lafayette, Citizen of Two Worlds," with the technical assistance of Ken Williams and Evan Earle.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834.; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834.; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier,marquis de, 1757-1834--Family.; Lafayette, Marie Adrienne (de Noailles), marquise de, 1759-1807.; Lafayette, Georges Washington Louis Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1779-1849.; Tessé, Adrienne Catherine de Noailles, comtesse de, 1741-1814.; Lafayette, Marie Adrienne (de Noailles), marquise de, 1759-1807.; Lafayette, Georges Washington Louis Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1779-1849.; Tessé, Adrienne Catherine de Noailles, comtesse de, 1741-1814.; Hénin, Etiennette de Montconseil, princesse d'.; Staël,Madame de (Anne-Louise-Germaine), 1766-1817.; Pinckney, Thomas, 1750-1828.; Du Pont de Nemours, Pierre Samuel, 1739-1817.; Shelley, Mary Wollstonecraft, 1797-1851.; Bentham, Jeremy, 1748-1832.; Owen, Robert, 1771-1858.; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826.; Marshall, John, 1755-1835.; Madison, James, 1751-1836.; Adams, John, 1735-1826.; Monroe, James, 1758-1831.; Jackson, Andrew, 1767-1845.; Webster, Daniel, 1782-1852.; Clay, Henry, 1777-1852.; Sparks, Jared, 1789-1866.; Willard, Emma, 1787-1870.; Wright, Frances, 1795-1852.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790.; Cadet de Gassicourt, C.-L. (Charles-Louis), 1769-1821.; Carnot, Lazare, 1753-1823.; France. Armée. Garde Nationale (Paris)
Subjects:
Domestic relations--France--History.; Administration of estates--France--History.; Administration of estates--United States--History.; Land tenure--France--History.; Land titles--Registration and transfer--France.; Land tenure--United States--History.; Land tenure--Law and legislation--France.; Land tenure--Law and legislation--United States.; Procedure (Law)--United States--History.; Abotionists -- France.; Abolitionists -- United States.; Slavery.; Paris (France). Garde nationale.
Places:
United States--History--Revolution, 1775-1783--Sources.; United States--Politics and government--19th century.; France--History--July Revolution, 1830--Sources.; Belgium--History--Revolution, 1830-1839--Sources.; France--Politics and government--19th century.; France--Economic conditions--18th century.; Paris (France)--Politics and government.; Paris (France)--History--1789-1799.; Guyana.; Haiti -- History.; Italy--History--Uprising, 1831--Sources.; Poland--History--Revolution, 1830-1832--Sources.; France--Foreign relations--United States.; United States--Foreign relations--France.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
This is a large guide and will take time to fully load.
HISTORY OF OWNERSHIP
Consisting of an enormous quantity of manuscripts as well as printed works, graphics, and other remembrances of the General, the collection had originally belonged to the Lafayette family and had been preserved at the family estate at Chavaniac. Early in this century it was sold to the Parisian antiquarian dealer, Dieudonné-Elie Fabius, who himself made substantial additions to the collection in the following decades.
PROVENANCE
The Lafayette Collection was created in the 1960's through the interest and generosity of Arthur H. and Mary Marden Dean. The first step was taken in 1963 with the purchase of the Chavaniac or "Fabius" collection of materials by and about General Lafayette. When it was purchased for Cornell in 1963, the manuscripts alone filled fifty-three cartons. The French government agreed to its export but only after three of the cartons, which contained papers relating to the French Revolutions of 1789 and 1830, were removed and deposited in the Archives Nationales. In 1966, once again through the generosity of the Deans, Cornell expanded its holdings when it acquired the Lafayette collection of Marcel Blancheteau, a noted Parisian book dealer. The new addition contained over 600 items, mostly printed and graphic materials, which complemented the manuscript character of the Fabius purchase. See Laurent Ferri, "How Lafayette Collections Were Built in the U.S.A. (and at Cornell University in Particular)", http://www.library.cornell.edu/insidecul/ May 2008.
RELATED MATERIAL
A large collection (ca. 650 v.) of books by and about Lafayette, including nearly all editions of his Mémoires and some books he owned, is also in the repository.
COLLECTION ARRANGEMENT
The Lafayette Collection consists of manuscripts, documents, and correspondence. Facsimiles are noted as such in the folder listing.
Series I, manuscripts, comprises unpublished written or printed material except for documents and original correspondence.
Series II, documents, comprises written and printed material that has official or legal import.
Series I and II are each divided into two sections: the first, material not written by Lafayette, is arranged alphabetically by name, place, or issuing institution. Manuscripts written by Lafayette come last and are arranged chronologically.
Series III, Lafayette's correspondence, has been divided into outgoing and incoming correspondence Outgoing is arranged chronologically except for the large Beauchet correspondence which is grouped together and comes last (Boxes 34-41). Incoming correspondence is divided into three subsections: in the first, correspondence is arranged alphabetically by name of sender; in the second, Boxes 87-89, general correspondence Lafayette received in 1830-1831 is arranged alphabetically by sender, but individual headings are not listed in the folder guide; in the third, Boxes 90-94, incoming American correspondence is arranged chronologically by year only, and alphabetically by sender within each year. Box 95 contains facsimiles of correspondence and letters from unknown senders from 1831-1834.
Series IV contains Lafayette family papers and is arranged as follows: manuscripts and documents and letters related to Madame Lafayette; manuscripts and documents related to George Washington Lafayette; letters from George Washington Lafayette arranged chronologically; letters to him arranged alphabetically; petitions received arranged alphabetically; papers associated with the Lafayette family in general.
In the folder listing, folder titles include dates and places, most derived from the item itself; some are supplied. Information supplied by the editor appears in brackets. Some dates refer to the French Revolutionary calendar; these are followed by the Gregorian equivalent in brackets. The folder listing is indexed, using headings derived from folder titles or supplied as necessary. When a page reference in the index does not adequately identify an item, it is followed by a specific citation (name and date) in brackets.
SERIES DESCRIPTIONS
- Series I. Manuscripts
  This series consists of notes and commentary by Lafayette and other prominent people; transcribed extracts from newspapers, books and letters; drafts of Lafayette's addresses and speeches; newspaper articles about Lafayette; poems, songs and addresses written as tributes to Lafayette; and papers dealing with family finances and properties. In "Note relative à ma fortune personelle," possibly written while he was in prison, Lafayette takes stock of the financial and property losses he had incurred in the Revolution. There are copies of the 16 letters, transcribed and bound with pink silk ribbon by Adrienne, which Lafayette wrote to her from America. Copies of Lafayette's letters from prison form a 44 page booklet. Papers associated with Lafayette's domain near Cayenne, French Guiana, provide information about colonial law, administration, labor and economic production and reflect Lafayette's interest in the cause of emancipation. Lafayette purchased the property in 1785 intending to make his plantation the site of an experiment in the "gradual emancipation" of the blacks who worked there. Related items include a list of the names, ages and families of the black people brought in to work on the plantation, a description of slave ships, a "Plan for the Gradual Abolition of Slavery in the U.S.", a proposal for a model settlement in French Guiana which was submitted to the National Assembly, and an ambitious and idealistic prospectus for La Société de Grandes Cultures Coloniales, which outlines in detail the establishment of large plantations for coffee, cocoa, indigo and cotton. In contrast to prospecti, an 1815 "exposé" by Geneste, Lafayette's agent in French Guiana, criticizes in detail the actual operations and productivity of plantations in Cayenne. Other topics covered include: the abdication of Napoléon; the 1824 American Tour; membership of the Society of the Cincinnati, etc.
- Series II. Documents
  This series contains many forms of printed and handwritten official documents that record the routine business of a professional soldier and member of the landed aristocracy, and the disruption of that routine by revolutionary historical events. These documents deal chiefly with Lafayette's military career, his financial affairs, and his landed property and estates. The affairs of Lafayette's family and ancestors are also represented here, although to a lesser extent. The older pieces in this series date primarily from the seventeenth and early eighteenth centuries, but extend as far back as the thirteenth century in a set of land deeds for the seignory of Langeac. In addition to land titles and deeds, family documents include birth, death and baptismal certificates, articles of marriage, wills and other inheritance-related material.
  Much of Lafayette's considerable fortune went to support the American and French Revolutions, and he was burdened by debts for many years thereafter. In 1793, Lafayette's first year in prison, his financial plight was assessed in "Etat général des Biens et des Dettes de M. de la Fayette". In this same year Lafayette drew a draft on the United States for "a sum of secret monney" meant to help him escape. Also dating from this period are documents associated with the arrest and imprisonment of Lafayette and his wife, and with the confiscation of much of their property. For example, in 1793, the French government produced a fifty-page appraisal, complete with atlas, of confiscated lands near Chavaniac, lands they sold in 1794. The attitude of the revolutionary government towards the nobility is suggested by another document which restricts the movement of particular individuals and limits their association with each other. Several documents announce the removal of various persons from the list of émigrés, and there are numerous passports for members of the Lafayette and Tessé families.